Guide to the Pittsburgh Speech and Society Project Collection, 2003-2005 AIS.2009.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Speech and Society Project Collection
2003-2005
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kiesling, Scott F.
Johnstone, Barbara
AIS.2009.02
1 Linear Feet (51 compact discs, 48 folders)
The Pittsburgh Speech and Society Project was conducted between 2003 and 2005 by Barbara Johnstone, Professor of Linguistics and Rhetoric at Carnegie Mellon University, and Scott F. Kiesling, Associate Professor of Linguistics at the University of Pittsburgh. The project involved recording interviews with Pittsburgh-born residents with the goal of studying the sociolinguistics of Pittsburgh speech, known informally as 'Pittsburghese.' The collection consists of 48 interviews on 51 compact disks as well as information about the interviewees, consent forms, and some transcripts. Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically at http://pittsburghspeech.pitt.edu/.
History
Barbara Johnstone, Professor of Linguistics and Rhetoric at Carnegie Mellon University, and Scott F. Kiesling, Associate Professor of Linguistics at the University of Pittsburgh, directed the Pittsburgh Speech and Society Project as a way to study the sociolinguistics of Pittsburgh speech, informally known as 'Pittsburghese.' The project involved casually interviewing people from four Pittsburgh-area neighborhoods with the goal of capturing unselfconscious speech. The interviews were designed to inquire about people's lives and attitudes about Pittsburgh, while investigating the local dialect. The project spanned 2003 through 2005, totaling 48 interviews. The project was made possible through funding by a U.S. National Science Foundation Collaborative Research award nos. BCS0417684 and BCS-0417657.
Scope and Content Notes
The Pittsburgh Speech and Society Project Collection consists of 51 CDs containing 48 interviews as well as information about the interviewees and the project itself. Interviews were conducted by one of three people, with the majority being conducted by project director, Barbara Johnstone. Subjects involved interviews with lone subjects, married couples, and one mother-son couple. The interviews were designed to study the aspects of Pittsburgh language and dialects, however, as many of the questions relate to families, neighborhood histories, local news and individual events, life experiences in Pittsburgh are also captured.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in two series. Series I consists of CDs containing audio WAV files of interviews and documents stored as PDF files. Series II contains printed versions of the PDF files from each CD. These documents include information about the Speech and Society Project as well as information on the subjects of the interviews and consent forms. Some interview transcripts are also included. Both series are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the interviewee.
Series I. CDs
Series II. Documents
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Barbara Johnstone in February 2009.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Compact discs require a computer to access audio content and PDF files of manuscript materials.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Speech and Society Project Coalition, 2003-2005, AIS.2009.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
The research and outcome of the project is documented on the Pittsburgh Speech & Society Project website.
Interviews; Speech -- Research; Dialects -- Study and teaching; English language -- Provincialisms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Sociolinguistics; Education; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Hill District (Pittsburgh, Pa.); East Liberty (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Lawrenceville (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Wilkinsburg (Pa.); Cranberry (Butler County, Pa.: Township); Forest Hills (Pa.); New Sewickley (Pa.: Township); Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social life and customs; Carnegie-Mellon University
- CDs, 2003-2005; I.; 1 box (51 items)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Each CD contains audio WAV files of the interviews as well as PDF files with information about the project. Information includes consent forms and some transcripts. Interviewee information includes name, birth date, sex, neighborhood of residence, occupation, and primary ethnic affiliation. The CDS are arranged alphabetically by last name of the interviewee.
  - Baltimore, Terri, March 3, 2005; (3 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 1)
  - Barton, Thomas and Rosemary, July 3, 2004; (3 PDF files, 11 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 2)
  - Becer, Allan, October 27, 2003; (4 PDF files, 7 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 3)
  - Broge, Maureen, November 5, 2003; (4 PDF files, 7 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 4)
  - Cherry, Dicken, June 28, 2004; (3 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 5)
  - Collins, Cynthia, December 15, 2003; (3 PDF files, 6 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 6)
  - Conley, Eric, July 28, 2005; 2 items ( 2 PDF files, 4 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 7-8)
  - Coy, Irma, March 14, 2005; (3 PDF files, 6 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 9)
  - Delaney, Kelly, February 7, 2004; (3 PDF files, 8 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 10)
  - Dickey, Stephanie, October 15, 2004; (3 PDF FILES, 12 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 11)
  - Estep, Mary and Lois Sharpe, July 7, 2004; (4 PDF files, 11 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 12)
  - Evans, Betty, September 22, 2003; (3 PDF files, 4 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 13)
  - Evans, Marcy, July 14, 2004; (3 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 14)
  - Evans-Potter, Gail, September 30, 2003; (4 PDF files, 5 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 15)
  - Fletcher, Linda, February 2, 2004; (3 PDF files, 6 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 16)
  - Folan, Maggie, December 1, 2003; (3 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 17)
  - Folan, Sally, November 14, 2003; (3 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 18)
  - Franciscus, Wilfred, September 20, 2003; (5 PDF files, 4 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 19)
  - Fuchs, Derek, January 10, 2004; (4 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 20)
  - Gallagher, Lisa, September 29, 2003; (3 PDF files, 4 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 21)
  - Gast, Mary and Robert, September 19, 2003; (3 PDF files, 4 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 22)
  - Glasser, Jamie, May 18, 2004; (3 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 23)
  - Gormley, Ken, October 21, 2003; (3 PDF files, 4 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 24)
  - Green, Kevin, February 2, 2005; (3 PDF files, 10 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 25)
  - Hamilton, Colleen, August 3, 2004; (3 PDF files, 6 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 26)
  - Hartman, John, January 9, 2004; (3 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 27)
  - Hill, Gloria, June 7, 2005; (3 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 28)
  - Hines, Joseph and Nellie, October 29, 2003; (5 PDF files, 10 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 29)
  - Jackson, Edwin, April 7, 2005; (3 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 30)
  - Johnson, Alex, July 4, 2005; (2 PDF files, 9 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 31)
  - Leisie, Frank, July 8, 2004; (3 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 32)
  - Leisie, Matthew Frank, July 27, 2004; (3 PDF files, 9 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 33)
  - Modrak, Rita and Herbert, July 20, 2004; (2 PDF files (no consent forms), 11 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 34)
  - Montague, Joelle, March 3, 2007; (2 PDF files, 1 audio file ) (Box 1, Disk 35)
  - Morris, Lynette, March 23, 2005; (3 PDF files, 6 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 36)
  - Nevel, Sandra and William, June 7, 2005; (3 PDF files, 4 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 37)
  - Nicholls, John, September 26, 2003; (3 PDF files, 6 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 38)
  - Pitard, Elizabeth and Derrick, September 12, 2003; (5 PDF files, 2 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 39)
  - Placone, Dorothy and Ronald, Sr., September 6, 2003; (4 PDF files, 6 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 40)
  - Placone, Ronald, Jr., May 25, 2004; (3 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 41)
  - Pressman, Janice, October 31, 2003; (4 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 42)
  - Roche, Karen, June 15, 2004; (3 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 43)
  - Schwartz, Walter, December 5, 2003; (3 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 44)
  - Trenz, John, November 14, 2003; (4 PDF files, 7 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 45)
  - Wudarczyk, Jude, November 29, 2003; (4 PDF files, 8 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 46)
  - Young, Demetrius, April 14, 2006; (2 PDF files, 10 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 47)
  - Young, Mary, June 28, 2005; 2 items (2 PDF files, 13 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 48-49)
  - Young-Coleman, Stacey, July 15, 2005; (2 PDF files, 12 audio files ) (Box 1, Disk 50)
  - Zielmanksi, Barbara, September 16, 2003; (5 PDF files, 5 audio files) (Box 1, Disk 51)
- Documents, 2003-2005; II.; 1 box
  This series contains documents that have been printed from PDF files on the original CDs. The information is arranged in folders, alphabetically, by interviewee last name. The amount of content varies from each interviewe, however, all files contain a short message about the Speech and Society Project as well as personal information about the interviewee. All but one file contain consent forms signed by the interviewees, and many contain transcripts of the interview.
  - Document files, 2003-2005 (Box 2)